<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>http://www.thomaslevine.com/</id>
  <title>Thomas Levine</title>
  <updated>2013-09-24T05:00:00Z</updated>
  <link rel="alternate" href="http://www.thomaslevine.com/"/>
  <link rel="self" href="http://www.thomaslevine.com/!/feed.xml"/>
  <author>
    <name>Thomas Levine</name>
    <uri>http://www.thomaslevine.com</uri>
  </author>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.thomaslevine.com,2013-09-24:/!/want/index.html</id>
    <title type="html">Things I want</title>
    <published>2013-09-24T05:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2013-09-24T05:00:00Z</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://www.thomaslevine.com/!/want/index.html"/>
    <content type="html">&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Pink fedora&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Stenotype (working on it)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Fast scanner for old papers
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;A book-scanner would be even better.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Many Injinji toe socks, specifically 
  &lt;a href="http://www.rei.com/product/711809/injinji-performance-series-original-weight-mini-crew-toesocks"&gt;these&lt;/a&gt;
  and &lt;a href="http://www.rei.com/product/728375/injinji-performance-series-original-weight-crew-toesocks"&gt;these&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;More TechWick shirts&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Soldering iron with a thin tip&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.thomaslevine.com,2013-05-05:/!/utility-of-cobalt/index.html</id>
    <title type="html">Utlity of Cobalt</title>
    <published>2013-05-05T05:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2013-05-05T05:00:00Z</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://www.thomaslevine.com/!/utility-of-cobalt/index.html"/>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;x.scraperwiki.com uses a new infrastructure for running scripts. We call it
&lt;a href="https://github.com/scraperwiki/cobalt"&gt;Cobalt&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It gives you HTTP APIs for creating computer boxes, running code inside them
and querying SQLite databases stored inside them. It also gives you a static
web server running on the box. We’ve been using it to run custom scripts for
our data services.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Setting up a project use Cobalt takes a minute, and figuring out how to use
Cobalt the first time takes a few minutes, so tiny projects might be better
off not using Cobalt. (I don’t use Cobalt for most things.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Making a Cobalt box is like making a virtual server, so it is sort of nice if
you want access to GNU/Linux without running it on your main computer or if
maintaining these services seems like too much work. But I still think it isn’t
great for tiny, simple projects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But if it’s not that hard for you to set up a static web server and a database
API and whatnot, it’s not that helpful that Cobalt has them. Loads of different
tools can already accomplish most of these components, so there’s probably an
easier way to set up a simple project than using Cobalt.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/!/utility-of-cobalt/doodle.png" alt="Manually drawn line plot of 'Utility of Cobalt' as a function of 'Project Complexity'" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The benefit of Cobalt comes in encapsulating different projects into different
computers and in standardizing the ways that different people do things.
Consider complexity to include the number of people working on the project and
to include any reasonable measure of code/architecture complexity, then look
at the doodle above.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have more than one person working on one project, it is nice to have
a standard way of doing things and a place to put everything. You could come
up with your own standards, but if Cobalt’s standards work for you, you might
as well use that. We know that the data will be in SQLite, that we can query
it through the web in a particular way, that they are in a particular computer
&amp;amp;c. That’s still not that interesting, though, because there are other ways to
standardize things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have more than one person working on one project, it is also nice not
to have to trust other people’s code. Rather than someone else’s code on my
computer, I can run it on the box. The box contains nothing but the project,
so I don’t have to worry about it breaking anything else. When projects involve
many different teams of people, you also might want to separate your project
across multiple boxes, one box per team. The standard Cobalt interfaces make
this a bit easier.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.thomaslevine.com,2013-03-21:/!/checkbook/index.html</id>
    <title type="html">On balancing checkbooks</title>
    <published>2013-03-21T05:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2013-03-21T05:00:00Z</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://www.thomaslevine.com/!/checkbook/index.html"/>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Balancing checkbooks is one of those things that people say everyone should
know how to do. It’s also one of those should learn in school or whatnot. I
jokingly arrogantly don’t see why.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I never learned to balance a checkbook in school, so when I wanted to account
better for money, looked for accounting software on SourceForge and found that
GnuCash had many downloads, recommendations, &amp;amp;c. Then I installed it and spent
a Sunday afternoon skimming the
&lt;a href="http://gnucash.org/docs/v2.4/C/gnucash-guide/index.html"&gt;GnuCash tutorial&lt;/a&gt;.
This was enough to satisfy me for
a while. &lt;!-- Replace this with a time in months or years--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This leads me to find it silly to learn/teach checkbook-balancing. First,
imputing data on paper is
silly these days because computers can transcribe things much more easily and
reliably than people can. Second, as far as I can tell, the “balancing” a
checkbook thing is just a buzzy word for reconciling, so it’s not really a big
deal. Third, checkbooks seem quite limited. Again, I’ve never properly learned,
but here are a bunch of things that seem annoying to do in a checkbook:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Split transactions&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Double-entry accounting&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Drawing graphs&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Multiple accounts&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In conclusion, I see no reason to teach people to balance their checkbooks;
just use some proper computer-based accounting system.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.thomaslevine.com,2013-02-20:/!/scarsdale-tax-rate/index.html</id>
    <title type="html">Scarsdale Village tax rates and inflation</title>
    <published>2013-02-20T06:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2013-02-20T06:00:00Z</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://www.thomaslevine.com/!/scarsdale-tax-rate/index.html"/>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I took some &lt;a href="https://github.com/tlevine/scarsdale-data/blob/master/budget/appendix_a1-tax.csv"&gt;information&lt;/a&gt;
out of the Scarsdale budgets and noticed that the property tax rate increases quite consisently.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/!/scarsdale-tax-rate/tax_rate_by_year.png" alt="Tax rate over time" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The property tax rate is a proportion of the assessed value of the house; if
your house is assessed at $10,000 and the tax rate is 24%, you pay $2,400 in
village taxes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On your bill and in the budget, it’s actually represented in permil rather
than percent; for every $1,000 of assessed value, you pay $240 in taxes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="" alt="Example budget" /&gt;
&lt;img src="" alt="Example bill" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyway, I was somewhat surprised by the consistent increase, so I looked a bit further.
I wondered whether the increase could be explained by inflation, so I plotted
the tax rate against the value of a dollar in today’s dollars based on the
Consumer Price Index. (This tries to adjust for inflation.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/!/scarsdale-tax-rate/adj_tax_rate.png" alt="Raw and inflation-adjusted tax rate over time" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This doesn’t look that different from the previous plot becauses the value of
a dollar changes quite consistently. I didn’t find it that helpful for figuring
out whether inflation explained the changes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next, I adjusted the tax rate for inflation. You can think of the adjusted tax
rate (dotted line) as the fair tax rate for each year if you were to pay for
that year’s taxes (the solid line) in 2009 rather than in the year to which
they correspond.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/!/scarsdale-tax-rate/tax_rate_by_inflation.png" alt="Tax rate as a function of inflation" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the increase in property tax rate is explained only by inflation, this line
should be flat. Well, it would have bumps, bu wouldn’t increase or decrease on
average. Aside from the shift in 2008, the line is sort of flat, but it does
tend upwards. This suggests to me that something other than general inflation
is increasing the property tax.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:www.thomaslevine.com,2013-02-15:/!/data-business-models/index.html</id>
    <title type="html">Data business models</title>
    <published>2013-02-15T06:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2013-02-15T06:00:00Z</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://www.thomaslevine.com/!/data-business-models/index.html"/>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I’ve been at loads of hip and non-hip data talks here and there and have come
four categories of data business model in this hip data ecosystem. Here they are.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Big storage for big people&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Money in, insight out: Vertically integrated data analysis&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Internal data analysis on an organization’s own data&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Quantitative finance&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h2 id="big-storage-for-big-people"&gt;Big storage for big people&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is mostly Hadoop. For example,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Teradata&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Hortonworks&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;MapR&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Cloudera&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some people are using NoHadoop. (I just invented this word.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Datastax (Cassandra)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Couchbase (Couch but not the original Couch)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;10gen (Mongo)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Either way, these companies sell consulting, training, hosting, proprietary
special features &amp;amp;c. to big businesses with shit tons of data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="money-in-insight-out-vertically-integrated-data-analysis"&gt;Money in, insight out: Vertically integrated data analysis&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Several places package data collection, analysis and presentation. I think this
is pretty close to “research”. One example is AIMIA, which manages the Nectar
card scheme; as a small part of this, they analyze the data that they collect
and present ideas to clients. Many producers of hip data tools also provide hip
data consulting, so they too fall into this category.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="data-hubs"&gt;Data hubs&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some companies produce suites of tools that approach this vertical integration;
when you use these tools, you still have to look at the data yourself, but it
is made much easier. This approaches the
‘&lt;a href="http://blog.scraperwiki.com/2012/03/09/from-cms-to-dms-c-is-for-content-d-is-for-data/"&gt;data hubs&lt;/a&gt;’
that Francis likes talking about.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lots of advertising, web and social media analytics tools fall into this
category. You just configure your accounts, let data accumulate, and look at
the flashy dashboard. You still have to put some thought into it, but the
collection, analysis and presentation are all streamlined and integrated and
thus easier for people who wouldn’t otherwise do this themselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tools like Tableau, ScraperWiki, RStudio (combined with its tangential R
services) also fall into this category. You still have to do your analysis, but
they let you do all of your analysis in one place, and connections between that
place, your data sources and your presentatino media are easy. Well that’s the
idea at least.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="internal-data-analysis"&gt;Internal data analysis&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Places with lots of data have internal person(s) do something with them. Any
company that’s making money must have something like this. The mainstream
companies might call these people “business analysts”, and they might do all
their work &lt;a href="http://blog.scraperwiki.com/2012/07/31/do-all-analysts-use-excel/"&gt;in Excel&lt;/a&gt;.
The hip companies are doing “data science” with open source software before it
gets cool. And the New York City government has a team that just analyzes New
York data to make the various government services more efficient. For the
current discussion, I see these as similar sorts of people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was pondering distinguishing between analysis that affects businessy
decisions from models that get written into software. Since I’m just
categorising business models and these things could both be produced by the
same guy working inside a company with lots of data, I chose not to distinguish
between them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="quantitative-finance"&gt;Quantitative finance&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Quantitative finance is special in that the data analysis is very close to a
product in itself; the conclusion of analysis or algorithm is “Make these
trades when that happens.” rather than “If you market to these people, you
might sell more products.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This has some interesting implications. For one thing, you could have a whole
company doing quantative finance. On a similar note, I suspect that analyses
can be more complicated because the analyses might only need to be conveyed to
people with quantitative literacy; in the other categories, it might be more
important to convey insights to non-technical managers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="conclusionary"&gt;Conclusionary&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pretend that I made some insightful, conclusionary conclusion in this sentence.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
</feed>

